this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hey this is Jeremy Jung for a
software engineering radio today I'm
speaking with Spencer Dixon Spencer has
been building websites for over 10 years
and is the CTO at touple a screen
sharing application for pair programming
I'll be speaking with Spencer about
building tuple using WebRTC and the many
challenges that come from building a
native application that requires low
latency and video communication Spencer
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks Jeremy I'm really excited to be
here first could you give a quick
introduction to what tuple is for our
listeners sure
so tuple is a remote screen sharing
application somewhat similar to Skype or
zoom or slack calls
however it's purpose-built for remote
pair programming specifically so all of
our design decisions rely around making
the best possible pair programming
experience that we can one of the things
about tuple is that you used web RTC to
allow for the screen sharing - in order
to see each person in order to see each
person's screen and all that before we
go into the specifics of building - boy
I kind of wanted to set up what are the
pieces that are in it so to start what
makes web RTC different and what is it
used for sure so it probably makes sense
to give a high-level view of like what
WebRTC is before going into what it's
used for it's really three things it's
less spec which provides information on
specific api's and then there's also the
implementation side of it which can be
found in Lib web RTC which is this
massive you know 5 million plus line C++
code base and all the major browsers use
that lib WebRTC to implement the spec in
their respective browsers so Google
Mozilla opera and those API is allow you
to share any sort of real-time media but
it doesn't have to just be media so one
aspect of WebRTC that's pretty useful is
the concept of creating data channels
so you can establish this connection
between two peers and then really send
whatever bytes of information you want
from point A to point B which has some
interesting use cases I know people have
built like BitTorrent clients using
WebRTC and but its primary uses for
capturing frames from the webcam or you
know your screen buffer and sending them
over to the other pier for the the data
channel you referred to is that for
everything that goes over web RTC or is
that only for specific types of data
yeah the data channels will send data
through SCTP and the audio and visual
audio and video data gets sent over RTP
and our TV actually is really two things
it's RTP and rtcp so there's the
real-time protocol and in the real-time
control protocol and rtcp allows the two
peers to kind of send diagnostic
information as to how the stream is
going so that way they can update in
real-time and I believe that WebRTC
actually uses some sort of extension to
RTP which allows it to send both those
two protocols on one port instead of I
think traditionally RTP you know you use
one port for the RTP and then you
increment it by one and that's what our
TCP gets sent on you said they allows
you to use the same port so then are
those two separate connections then to
the same port nope so it's one
connection that all this kind of gets
multiplexed over I believe you mentioned
how so our TCP that's once two clients
are connected to one another kind of
updating on how the stream is going
would that allow for things such as like
if one client is is getting a little
slow that it could talk they could talk
to one another to say like oh I'm gonna
lower the video quality or is it more
for just like hey things are going bad
but it doesn't really there's not much
you can do about it yeah it's a good
question I think at that level of the
stack it's not making any intelligent
decisions like that most of those
decisions are happening a bit higher and
that's part of you know the magic of the
WebRTC video and audio pipelines they're
listening into those are TCP responses
to kind of get an idea of how much
jitter it there is in the network
how the packet loss is and adjusting the
situation to be optimal for that cool
and you were saying that RTP that's
where the actual video and audio data is
that's how that's being transmitted yep
and that's built on top of UDP which is
oh so it's UDP and then DTLS so d TLS is
Datagram transport security layer or
layer security it's the equivalent of
TLS in the TCP world but for UDP so it's
very important that you know all the
packets are encrypted and somebody can't
you know listen in and then the packets
after DTLS go through s RTP and s are
tcp which is just the secure version of
those a lot of protocols yeah and so
like UDP it has like no guarantees in
terms of you send a packet via UDP and
the other right so there's no
reliability and the order that packets
are going to be received so they can be
in an in order out of order and then you
also no longer get certainty that the
packet will have arrived in TCP you do
get those things you're guaranteed to
get packets in order and if they're
packet gets lost it'll do a
retransmission and you'll receive the
packet the real reason that UDP is much
better for this situation is because
it's a lot lower latency but it also
means that the WebRTC pipeline has to do
a tremendous amount of work to make up
for error correction or in some cases it
even will ask for a retransmission of
packets given the current context like
if it's going to be cheaper to ask for
the retransmission so let's say the the
round-trip time between p1 and p2 is
very low oftentimes it'll be cheaper to
just ask to retransmit the packet then
do something else
so the data channels which use SCTP the
that's the main reason why they use SCTP
is to be able to kind of configure the
data channels to be in a row viable
state if you wanted them to be so I
don't actually know too much about
stream control transmission protocol but
the easiest way to think about it is it
allows you to simulate a TCP or TLS
environment using underlying UDP packets
okay SCTP that would be something that
you would use maybe if you didn't have
such a low latency requirement or when
would you use that instead of using RTP
yep that'd be one example or you know
4-tuple there are certain messages that
we want to make sure no matter what they
go from point A to point B and so our
data channels are configured to be
reliable and and send those messages in
order for example I mean imagine if you
were moving your cursor on the hosts
machine and the packets started coming
in out of order that would look super
wonky if you saw that cursor jumping all
over the place from you know point A to
point B so we want to make sure that
those messages are getting sent in order
and the fact that they're reliable is
maybe a little bit less important but
the end order aspect for that use case
for example would be something that we
care a lot about and is that because in
the case of audio and video there is
sort of something higher in the stack
that's taking care of things that are
out of order or things that are being
dropped whereas in the case of the
moving someone else's cursor example
there isn't that sort of thing in place
is that kind of the thinking yeah I
think that's the right way to think
about it so the cursor example that's
very much at the application level so
tuple we've come up with our own
protocol for how we want to send cursor
data we do some fancy stuff like caching
to make things a little bit quicker but
for the most part that's all defined by
us where the audio and video stuff
that's all being handled by WebRTC and
Webber TC has a number of different
buffers along the pipeline that enable
it to fix out of order packets and then
also allow for smooth play out so for
example like one of the core
abstractions in WebRTC is the concept of
a track like a media track and a track
could be audio it could be video it
could be the screen and if you associate
an audio track with a webcam track into
a stream then WebRTC does all this magic
for you where it'll properly buffer the
audio and the webcam and then the play
out will occur so that way you know the
person's mouth actually looks like
they're talking instead of being totally
off so
somewhat of a double-edged sword like is
sometimes you don't want that right
4-tuple
for example we actually don't care if
the audio is synced to the screen care
more about low or latency and we want
that as soon as you click a button on
someone's screen you know you see that
the feedback so we intentionally
disassociate the audio track with that
with that specific video track and tuple
in order to get some latency benefits
from there the other thing like when
we're talking about audio and video
being handled by WebRTC there's a
concept of a codec so could you explain
like what a codec is sure yeah codec
takes in a raw image and compresses it
to as best as it can based on different
parameters you kind of specify what you
care about and then part of the codec is
decoding so that's the end coding stage
then then it gets sent across the
network through Webber to see and then
then there's the decoding stage where it
takes that encoded frame and brings it
back to its original form
sometimes they're lossy sometimes
they're lossless depending on what
settings you have in different codecs
are better at different things for
example like h.264 is not as good at
encoding very very large frames like 4k
displays compared to something like vp9
so how did you decide which codec to
choose when you were working on tuple
that's a good question so WebRTC already
has a number of codecs built in or
rather like implementations of using the
codecs and we tested out vp8 vp9 h.264
with all sorts of different settings one
of the big value-adds 4-tuple is we
allow you to send the full resolution of
your display if you want to which turns
out to be very useful when you're
reading small text in text editor for
example so in doing those performance
tests vp9 just outperformed all of the
other ones like significantly on these
higher resolutions screens and so that's
why we went with that vp9 is just a
newer version of vp8 and then the V p10
actually got merged into what's called a
v1 there's a whole bunch of big
companies who've kind of merged together
to build the next generation
of codex because codex are one of the
most complicated pieces of software and
computer science probably and any one
company doing it by itself it like it's
just a lot of work and so Google was
generous enough to kind of offer you
know their resources and the current
work they had going for vp9 to merge it
into this new like consortium we are
actually in the process or I am in the
process of looking into using h.264
hardware accelerated encoding so that
whole process I was just explaining
there's a built-in assumption in my
explanation that this was all happening
at the software layer but a lot of
devices actually have hardware
implementations of that encoding step or
or the decoding step and so max do have
h.264 hardware encoders built into them
and so now that we have introduced the
webcam into two-pole which for a long
long time it was just the screen there's
definitely a lot of optimizations we can
do by pushing some of that load from CPU
over to the GPU and the plan is to
hopefully get hardware accelerated and
encoding working for those webcam
streams because those we don't let get
very big I think the max resolution on
those is like 320 by something 240 it's
small we only have a small little webcam
so if I understand correctly then you
would capture someone's video from say a
camera and that that imagery is it
originally in an uncompressed format and
then you have to take that uncompressed
imagery and compress it using a codec
but if the hardware of the machine like
say on a Mac has hardware support for
h.264 or something else then the GPU can
actually perform the encoding and
decoding instead of the CPU yeah you got
it so in some of the webcams they
actually will have encoding built into
the webcam so you get an encoded frame
already I believe but that's not like a
use case that were worried about at all
what you explained is exactly right and
for example on most iPhones and phones
they all have h.264 hardware decoding
and it's very useful for extending
battery life which is partially
part of the reason why they do it and
does that apply also to desktop capture
as well when you capture the screen and
you send it over the wire that's also
going through that same encoding process
yep yep same same general concept
capturing the frame that the capturing
step is there's a tremendous amount of
optimizations that occur there as well
luckily WebRTC actually already had a
pretty good
capturing set up which I believe they
actually grabbed from chromium and there
was a couple bugs in it we had to work
out but instead of capturing the entire
frame buffer what it does is it listens
for like diffs so it'll only it'll keep
like a local version of what the frame
buffer is and then whenever things
change on the screen it'll receive a
callback like this is a low-level
display stream callback in Mac OS and
it'll get that diff and then it'll
update it's it's representation of what
the frame buffer looks like and then
it'll pass that along to the next step
which then goes to the encoder to be
encoded and sent across the wire
interesting so in web the web RTC
libraries implementation they have sort
of already done the work to hook into
all these different operating systems
and have the operating system tell them
what's changed on the screen so that's
the only part they have to send is that
is that right not entirely right so
let's kind of break that down so yes
WebRTC provides lots of default
implementations for a lot of the big
core components that you end up needing
and that capturing part specifically
which you were just talking about it
does send the whole frame to the encoder
and then the encoder actually is in
charge of doing lots of very intelligent
temporal and spatial diffs to figure out
what's changed and then only send the
pieces over that have changed but more
what I mean is in the capturing phase
instead of it'll just look for the
screen updates and update the diffs in
that specific part of the pipeline if
that makes sense
I don't know I'm doing a bad job of
explaining it I think I well let's see
if I was understanding correctly so the
part words checking for the diffs that's
specifically at the capturing stage so
that's it has like I guess a frame that
it know
like okay this is what's currently on
the person's screen and in order to
update that capture and it's hooking
into the operating system is is that
correct yeah that's right so that allows
the capture times to go from you know
tens of milliseconds to sub ten
milliseconds because if you had to
capture a very big 5k display the
original display stream API is that Mac
provided didn't have this sort of
dipping available and it might just take
a significant chunk of time to do to do
that like give me everything that's on
the screen right now we're third capture
kinda have some intelligence built into
to not need to do that which is nice we
there were some things in their capture
actually in the early days that really
hurt us from a latency perspective so
they have this concept of like window
exclusion so let's say I want to capture
the entire screen but I don't want to
capture you know the window that has the
webcam on it so the other person's face
well though their exclusion code was
somewhat naive in the sense that it
would iterate over all of the windows in
on the screen and kind of like recreate
the pixels that would be behind that
screen that you want to exclude and that
actually ended up being very slow
depending on the size of the exclusion
and and how many windows were on your
display so we've had to do some things
to kind of tweak and optimize that in
the specific webcam instance what I do
is I actually capture the frame as
normal with the webcam on it and then I
go to that pixel buffer which is just
you know a big array of the the bytes of
the pixels and I I just turn all of the
ones that the you know the square where
the webcam is I just turned them all to
a different color and so that way that I
do this before even going into the
encoder so that way the encoder is not
worried about trying to encode two
different types of video right like
there's the screen video and then the
webcam video and there's lots of
different optimizations that encoders
can be tuned to to do well in one
scenario versus the other scenario and
we've spent all of our time and like
testing and trying to get the our vp9
implementation to do very well for the
screens and so by by you know sending in
a video on top of that it does us a
disservice so I kind of like get around
that problem by writing out those
those pixels before feeding it into the
encoder right so the the WebRTC I guess
screen capture part is your allowing it
to capture the whole screen and capture
the sort of webcam video and then you're
sort of going into there blanking out
all the pixels where you know the webcam
window is showing and then then you send
that over to the encoder and to the
encoder it looks like nothing has a
change it's just change just this box
and yeah white box black box whatever
colour we actually I actually changed
the colour based on if they're on Mojave
if they're in darker light mode so I try
and make it look you know good for
whatever mode they're in oh nice it's
pretty slick another part of web RTC I
want to kind of go into is there's this
idea of a session description protocol
could you kind of describe a little bit
about what that is
yeah really this gets down to like the
establishing a connection between two
peers and the overall protocol is called
ice so it stands for interactive
connectivity establishment it might make
sense to go through an example of like
how a normal call would would start I
haven't used the JavaScript API is in
like over a year since when we first
started working at tuple so I might get
this a little bit wrong but do my best
so initially you want to create a peer
connection and you pass into that peer
connection constraints and so the
constraints are you know I want audio or
I want video and this is really the
power of web right you see the fact that
you can just say video true at the
JavaScript JavaScript layer and it just
does all this magic to figure out how to
capture the video and set up the encoder
for you you don't need to do any of that
in the JavaScript API so once you have
your peer connection before even that
you need some sort of what I like to
call application signaling and that's a
process where you know let's say we have
Alice and Bob and Alice sees that Bob is
online she needs some way to ask Bob if
he's ready for a call right now and
however she wants to do that is fine
like most people end up using a
WebSocket server and she just sends a
message over to Bob and Bob can accept
her decline but assuming you know Bob is
ready to go and he accepts then Alice
will show you call navigator
get user media given those constraints
so this will signify to the browser like
hey go ahead and get those capturers
going you know start getting frames from
the screen or start getting frames from
the webcam and once it's got those
frames it'll give back some some media
tracks and then Alice can add those
media tracks to her peer connection and
then create the initial offer so when
she creates the initial offer that's
when the SDP gets created I know there's
a million acronyms I'm sorry but um the
the SDP is is basically just this really
big string of super esoteric like
letters and colons and magic numbers
that will tell Bob you know what
capabilities Alice is looking for in the
call so for example things that are on
there might be you know she's trying to
do video she's trying to do audio and
inside the video section it might say
her computer is capable of doing vp9 vp8
or h.264 so if Bob only has the ability
to do h.264 maybe he's on like a phone
or something then the web Weber TC will
allow them to negotiate this session
with just h.264 so that's really the
whole point of the STP is for the two
peers to be able to share like what
their capabilities are and preferences
so you can also explicitly say like in
this call I want to use you know this
encoder implementation she calls create
offer that STP gets generated and pretty
much every single step in this process
is async so you kinda have to wait for
callbacks to get called once she gets
that offer she then needs to send it to
Bob and how she does that again doesn't
really matter she could write it down on
a piece of paper and send it to him and
this process would still technically
work I've messed around with some WebRTC
stuff where I just copy and paste this
STP from one computer to the other so
this this part is totally left up to you
as the developer and an application
builder sends that to Bob Bob will set
that SDP as his remote description and
then he will create an answer
given that STP and once that answer gets
created another STP is generated on
Bob's side
Bob will set that as his local
description and then send that back to
Alice and then once Alice receives Bob's
STP then the process enters into this
ice interactive connectivity stage and
yeah so what happens there is on each
WebRTC client there's what's called an
ice agent and the ice agent is
responsible for gathering what are
called ice candidates so an ice
candidate is just a IP port pair and the
first thing that the ice agent will do
is it'll gather all of its local
candidates and then it uses a process
called stun to gather any remote
candidates so stun servers are stands
for session traversal utility is for NAT
and it's really a tool for NAT hole
punching which I think was originally
created by like video game developers
but could be wrong but stun servers are
very simple you're basically just making
a request to this server that's publicly
available on the Internet and that's
very important like that server has to
be publicly available on the Internet
and the server just responds back with
with IP and port you made that request
with and Google actually hosts a stun
server that most people use in the early
days to get going with WebRTC it's very
highly recommended to not use Google
stun server in a production environment
because for all you know it could go
down one day and then none of your users
will be able to connect and make calls
for two-pole we actually pay Twilio for
access to a stun and turn server all
right so the ice agent on each peer has
gathered the local candidates they've
gathered the remote candidates through
making requests to the stun server and
then the final step is like what's
called connectivity checks so you have
this array of these ice candidates which
are those IP port pairs and it organizes
them based on a set of priorities and as
a developer you do have some say and
that priority if you want or you can
just let WebRTC you make an intelligent
decision generally it's going to try and
start with the local candidates first
and it's going to fall back to the
remote and then the final candidates
that we'll use are what are called turn
candidates so
sorry this is so much but turn is a way
for the two peers to still have a call
if for some reason they can't establish
a connection peer to peer so a turn
server just relays packets from point A
to point B and for the most part I think
all turn servers are also stun servers
like I think it'd be weird to have a
turn server that didn't also implement
the stun protocol it does those
connectivity checks where the two peers
try and communicate with each other
based on that ordered list of vise
candidates and as soon as one is
successful then the connection gets
established and throughout the call you
know that might change maybe the the
network path that was chosen ends up
being no good anymore and so ice the ice
state will change throughout the course
of a call to disconnecting for example
and as an application developer it's
your responsibility to you know pop open
a reconnecting window or let the user
know that the call is not connected and
oftentimes ice will recorrect itself so
it'll just keep going down you know that
prioritized list of candidates until it
finds one that's good and if you have
turns setup it's it is optional you
don't have to have turn setup and it
does cost a lot of money because you
have a lot of bandwidth going through
these turn servers relaying you know
potentially big frames of media data but
eventually if you have turn it should
always connect because the turn server
is always publicly available in the
internet so if a peer can't connect with
turn it means they have other issues
going on most likely so let me see if I
can unpack this so to start you have the
sort of initial file that describes what
kind of codec and what kind of bandwidth
is available to each client and Duke
what sort of IPs and ports they have
available and so that's both you know
both peers have to create a file that
has this information and then you need
some way of sharing this file outside of
WebRTC so you said that could be through
WebSocket or like you said you could
even just copy and paste the text right
yep and then you mentioned how there is
a there's a stun server and that is
because it sometimes
machines can't connect to one another
directly and you have to find some way
of going through the NAT of each user
and I guess the stun server helps to
negotiate that yep that's right
and then you said there's a turn and I
don't remember what that acronym is but
oh it's traversal using relays around
NAT okay and so if the two users are
unable to establish a direct connection
through the stun server then the video
or the audio data will go to the turn
server and then will be streamed from
the other client from the turn server so
it's no longer a peer-to-peer connection
yep yeah you got it
and the turn servers are pretty dumb
they just relay you know the packets
from point A to point B so in the case
of tuple do you establish a peer-to-peer
connection first and then fall back to a
turn server or what does that look like
in tuple yeah that that's always the
ideal case and and for you know
real-world metrics I would say anywhere
in the range of 88 94 percent of the
connections can can be established
without turn so it's very low percentage
that end up actually needing turn in the
early days we actually did not support
turn but then occasionally you know we'd
get support tickets with people saying
we weren't able to connect and to be
honest the experience when you're using
turn it's just it's not fantastic
because you're adding all this
additional latency but there is a
certain level of importance and just
being able to let the clients connect
even if it isn't going to be the
greatest experience at least they're
able to collaborate a little bit or even
like have some audio going so we use
Twilio for that service we don't manage
our own turn servers there are very
popular open source libraries I think Co
turn is the is the big one and then
there's there are other companies that
do hosted turn servers for you I think
Dirk C's is one of the other big names
but we've we had all used Twilio in the
past for other companies and we're
familiar with their Docs and ap is and
stuff so we set that up and as far as
when in the process you need to
configure turn when you go to create a
peer connection you you can pass in a
configuration object and
configuration object will have the URLs
of the stun servers that you want to use
and you can use multiple stun servers so
it can you know backup to one if one is
not reachable and you also provide it
with the turn URL and so when we go to
create a call first we have to make a
request to Twilio and get you know a new
auth token to then pass in for that turn
URL and this information about stun and
turn is this embedded into that text
file you're talking about that has the
codec metadata and so on no so there's
actually two two parts of it so the SDP
gets created that has all the media
information and then once you've set I
believe I'm not high person certain but
I think once you set the remote
description that's when the ice agent
kicks in and starts generating these ice
candidates and so you'll have this
callback that's like on on ice Candidate
essentially and you are also responsible
for sending each of those ice candidates
over to the other pier because they both
need to have that list in order to do
the the connectivity checks and there is
another thing just to make this even
more confusing called trickle ice where
in the original ice implementation and
the early days of WebRTC it the time to
connect calls was very slow because it
both the ice agents needed to collect
all of the possible ice candidates
before starting to test them and see if
things were if they were able to connect
but there was a new spec released a
couple years ago i at this point i think
that allowed the ice candidates to start
checking a little bit sooner like kind
of like just in time like as they're
coming in and so that speeds up the
connection process significantly and we
do that with so we do what's called
trickle ice so as soon as we get that
ice candidate we send it to the other
peer so that way they can start testing
them out and seeing if they're able to
establish a connection with each other
cool I think that's like we've got a
pretty good overview of sort of what
WebRTC is and sort of what the different
pieces are so next I want to sort of go
more into building tuples specifically
tuple is like you said it's a pair
programming application so you have the
webcam capture you have the desktop
capture you have remote control of each
other's machine
and then of course as with any SAS
application you have billing and
accounts and so on and so forth so when
you first started working on tuple how
did you decide what to build first
mm-hmm it's a good question I think in
the very early days it was a lot about
just validating if we could do certain
things so for example one thing that was
very important to us is as a developer I
constantly use command tab to cycle
through my various applications and so
we wanted to validate like can we
remotely send a command tab from machine
1 to Machine 2 it's that way they can
feel as if they're local so that was
like something we wanted to validate
very early on and even before that was
can we even you know establish a
connection between the two the two peers
luckily WebRTC actually makes that that
initial spike phase very fast like I
think the within our first weekend of
kind of getting going on to pool we had
like a real screen sharing app that sent
the screen from A to B and you could
move the mouse around the thing was that
was all an electron in these very high
level of JavaScript API s and the
performance was not nearly as good as
what we what we wanted when you're
referring to the performance is that the
latency or what what was the part that
was an issue in the browser yeah latency
and quality there's a lot of constraints
that let's see what's a good way of
explaining it so WebRTC like I said is
this you know very very large code base
and they expose a lot of things with
their api's which allow you to hook into
the system for example like creating
your own video encoder or doing the
capturing on your own but there's also a
lot of parameters that are built into
that video pipeline and that audio
pipeline where the browser just made
certain decisions because the browser
has its own goals right like the browser
doesn't want to use up all your
resources people already complain about
you know chrome using up a high
percentage of their CPU well there are
certain things that chrome though in the
way that they use lib WebRTC they ensure
that you know the CPU gets throttled and
if it's using a certain amount then it's
going to downgrade the quality of the
stream or you know make certain
trade-offs and we recognized very early
on
like if we were going to use WebRTC in
the context of electron we just weren't
going to be able to push the needle as
far and as fast as we wanted to and
that's really what kind of led to us
extracting out you know that initial
spike into C++ and a swift
implementation so it's basically Chrome
or the web browser is they have their
own web RTC implementation or they're
using the the library I guess that was
created in C++ is that correct yeah so
chromium will use lib WebRTC and then
they'll kind of tweak certain settings
and like for example a classic one is
they have a bandwidth cap like each peer
connection I think can only have two
megabits per second or bandwidth so like
we we the first thing we did was
increase that cap and just doing that
allows us to send a higher quality frame
and most of the time that's just fine
because people are at least for our
target market they have good internet so
that cap doesn't necessarily they don't
care about that right is that something
that you don't have control over when
you're running and say chromium yeah or
just the JavaScript API so the
JavaScript API is our very high level
you don't really get much control I mean
it's it's it's the blessing and a curse
like you're able to get something going
very quickly but as soon as you start
wanting to do something very specific
you run into these pain points where
like if we wanted to continue down the
electron route we probably would have
had to build a custom version of
chromium with our custom version of
WebRTC that then we built a custom
version of electron with that custom
version of chromium if that makes sense
which we could have done and looking
back at it now you know it'd be
interesting to see what that would look
like but I would have taken along too it
was been a real big pain to do honestly
yeah I mean I guess it's sort of the
sort of thing where you start going down
that road and you're not sure what you
can or can't do or whether it was a good
idea until you really try it right yeah
and then I know chromium has this whole
concept of sandboxing and so I imagine
if we had gone down that route there
would be a lot of fighting with that
sandbox environment like there's a lot
of things that we need access to and API
is that you know we wouldn't be able to
distribute our app on the App Store
because even just to do that like
command
tab thing you need sudo privileges
essentially to be able to do that yeah I
think I remembered hearing that screen
here which was a screen sharing
application that came before when they
were acquired by slack they were kind of
asked to like try and make it work as an
electron app and it sounded like they
had a lot of difficulties a lot of
struggles with doing that so so maybe
maybe native is the way to go ya know
for sure we talked to those guys like we
definitely think of ourselves as the
spiritual successor to screen here like
we were 100% inspired by them to build
this company and we're very friendly
with their founders and they've given us
a lot of tips and advice over over the
year or so and we're very grateful for
that
Don's helped me with some of my mouse
implementation stuff and fras has given
us good tips on other things so very
cool kind of after all this you you
first started you experimented with
using chromium using the JavaScript API
s and then ultimately decided to to move
towards building a native app yeah it's
just it's interesting like from going
from electron the first step was
actually going there the next step was
going to Swift we actually didn't want
to do any C++ stuff so at the time we
hired somebody to help us fix the WebRTC
Mac SDK so there was actually already
like pretty pretty well built out SDK
and Swift an objective-c for interacting
with these low-level C++ WebRTC API is
but it wasn't working like it wasn't
compiling that's a been a common thread
unfortunately and my usage of WebRTC is
oftentimes the Mac the Mac stuff kind of
gets they don't really ensure it's
always up-to-date or gonna work properly
there's a lot of like a lot of that kind
of been put on us yeah so we originally
hired him - his name was Sam he was the
one of the first engineers that sketch
actually sketched out the prototyping
tool and he built like a web RTC
framework for us which we then used for
awhile and even that we decided we
didn't have enough customization over
the different parameters that we wanted
and that we'd have to go and another
layer deeper the web RTC Mac SDK is that
something that is
built into the operating system or is
that a open source project like where's
that coming from
that's coming from lib WebRTC so they
have Objective C bindings to all their
C++ code and one of the beauties of
Swift is you can bridge Objective C to
Swift relatively easily and so we were
able to call into those C++ api's
through Swift doing that in Swift and
Mac development cocoa development in
general their libraries are called
frameworks and so Sam basically built us
this like web web RTC framework that we
were able to to use to to get going in
the early days and I'm honestly very
grateful looking back that that was the
progression because you know prior to
tuple I've only been building websites
my entire life I never built
you know native application before and
there's a whole lot of stuff to learn in
just building cocoa applications and Mac
development in general and so by getting
this opportunity to kind of like ease
into it I mean I was definitely very
stressed at the time and I've but if I
had had to jump into the C++ at that
point I don't like I would have been way
too stressed I don't know what would
have happened so getting a comfortable
with the Mac development first and then
going into the C++ stuff was a good
progression I would say yeah so let's
see there's the Lib web RTC which is a
C++ API and they provided an objective-c
wrapper for that as a part of the
official project yeah but it sounded
like that wrapper was somewhat out of
date yeah okay so for perspective WebRTC
has like 200 commits a week on the
project and it moves really really fast
especially I think in the early days is
moving even faster than it is now but
they'll often change like the correct
way of doing things so even in the one
year that I've been working in it
they've changed how to do some of the
like track and stream management um so
like we've had to kind of like you know
adopt the new practices for that and and
a byproduct of that is if they're
changing things a lot the SDKs don't
always stay up-to-date so Sam who was
already an expert in Objective C and
Swift helped us kind of get that caught
up for our needs essentially just
porting over the specific API as we knew
we we needed at the time
to be able to get the calls going and
everything looking back at it like there
was a ton of things that we now use from
WebRTC that he didn't pour it over so
you know it's good that we now are just
able to do that ourselves and whenever
we need new stuff we kind of rewrite all
this glue code to make it work there's a
surprisingly large amount of glue code
between different languages and tuple I
think altogether we have seven different
languages that we use which can get
somewhat confusing for my brain
sometimes so that's yeah I mean that's
pretty pretty wild so you said you you
had a background just in building
websites and web development and now
you're in an environment where you're
working with seven different languages
so I guess how did you how did you
tackle that how did you start piecing
together you know what to learn and how
to do that for me
the way I learned best is through
reading books and building little sample
projects that test the knowledge of the
books that I read and then I'll often go
back and reread the sections that we're
confusing to me or that I think are
important for me to know better so a lot
of that I probably read like 50 or 60
books this last year Wow I've like
stacks and stacks of C++ books Coco
books objective-c books Swift books and
as I was reading them I would I would
build static site generator and
blackjack were usually my my first two
projects in each language
I think static site generators are
actually like a very good like get your
feet wet into a new language type of
project because in walls networking and
async stuff involves reading the file
system involves templates and basically
all the main things you touch in a
language you kind of get by building a
static site generator especially if you
you you get like you know parsing
command line argh
and all of that so that was my main
strategy then we did once we started
getting some revenue which was awesome
Ben did an amazing job of actually pre
selling some tuple before we even had
the product we used a lot of that money
in the early days to consult with
experts so a couple people that Sam guy
told you about who worked at sketch he
kind of helped get the initial Xcode
project set up and
you know there's this there's this thing
whenever you change languages after
you've done a project or two in that
language you have you know more opinions
on how you would set up the structure of
the projects no and you know once you
know the ecosystem better and one thing
I just didn't know anything about was
Xcode or how to properly set up you know
packages to be libraries and stuff like
that and so Sam kind of helped guide us
in that which it seems so simple and
silly to have paid someone for that
looking back but like now I know all
that stuff very well but it gave us a
lot of confidence knowing that we had a
strong foundation and that you know the
frameworks we were building to be
reusable and stuff were set up properly
yeah lots of YouTube videos talking to
experts building lots of side projects
and kind of taking like one topic at a
time and trying to isolate it from the
rest of the parts that that was very
useful basically reading a ton of books
building small projects having some
consulting help one thing I did want to
ask too is is about WebRTC specifically
were there any specific resources you
used or did you have someone you
consulted with to learn about that yeah
unfortunately the the resources for
learning WebRTC are not the greatest I
would say compared especially if you're
coming from the web world where you know
there's somebody who has written some
sort of ebook or tutorial series that
you could just buy for X dollars and
kind of level up on that topic quickly
for WebRTC the best source the source of
truth is just reading the header files
really like most of what I know about
native WebRTC has been from reading the
code that's not a great answer and I
hate when people give me an answer like
that so some other good resources are
WebRTC hacks that's forget the gentleman
who runs that but we had lunch with him
I won't plant in the early days and he
gave us some good tips and resources as
well cosmos software dr. Alex he's a PhD
in video encoder and he's like multiple
PhDs and he's been in doing WebRTC since
the early days like 2012-2013 something
like that he's extremely knowledgeable
he's very prolific in the Google Groups
there's a was like a WebRTC Google group
and he's always answering questions and
helping beginners and so I would
definitely recommend you know not being
shy and that goo
group and people are generally pretty
nice as long as you've done your
research and/or provide you know good
examples of what you've tried and what
hasn't worked then people are you know
very very willing to give you some tips
and yeah the I guess just if you're if
you're working at the higher level of
abstraction the Mozilla Doc's are really
good so the Mozilla Doc's have some
great examples of how to use the various
JavaScript API is there's a fantastic
book called high-performance browser
networking I forget the author's name I
think it's like Igor or something that
has a good section on WebRTC and just in
general is a great book for anybody
who's doing networking or web
development talks a lot about you know
tcp slow-start and various things to
improve the performance of your web apps
cool yeah those would be my go-to that's
a lot yeah you know honestly just
building building stuff to just build
some little side projects it's a great
way to learn yeah well we'll be sure to
get all these links into the show notes
definitely the other thing I guess I
wanted to ask about is you mentioned
that you're using seven languages so I
kind of wanted to get a better picture
of why are there so many languages
involved in the project I think that the
main reason why we have so many
languages is because we had certain
expertise --is in Prior languages and
therefore we were a lot more effective
at building parts of the application in
those languages a lot of the decisions
we made like it it's very clear that
like this language is the best for doing
this type of thing and therefore that's
why we should be using it for this but
there are like some situations I would
say where if we if I had just already
been an expert C++ developer like maybe
I wouldn't have done so much in Swift or
objective-c right
but yeah so like we have Ruby for our
back-end api's Ruby in rails and we were
all rails developers so that made sense
we can move quickly we have JavaScript
for our partially on the backend side
there's a little JavaScript and then
also our UI inside the application I
basically ended up building a electron
inside of our app that lets me call
JavaScript code and Swift code together
it's kind of bridges those and the
primary motivator behind that was I
originally started off building all
these native NS views and
it takes a long time like if you're
coming from a web background where you
can spin up you know a basic website
with some CSS and an hour or 15 minutes
and then you go to this native world
where it might take me an entire day
just to build a button that like kind of
looks not like what I actually want it
to look the difference in that time is
is drastic like I I do think that one
day tuples entire UI will probably be
native but we went to we I mean I don't
want to say we wouldn't have survived as
a start-up but it would have taken so
long to get to the UI to where it is
right now if I hadn't just written it
all in JavaScript which I and I'm very
fast and like our current UI probably
took me like a weekend to do that was
like the least time sync out of the
entire project hmm and then the Swift
because it's a lot more fun and fast to
develop in Swift than it is Objective C
or C++ so we try and do like the minimal
amount of C++ and C code that we need to
interface with these low-level API is
because a lot of api's are just easier
to interface with and C++ or C or were
communicating a lot with WebRTC so it
makes sense to kind of keep that code
all co-located and then Objective C and
Objective C plus plus are what allow us
to call into the C++ libraries that we
have in Objective C and then that
Objective C gets bridged over to the
Swift
so I think that's all the languages C
Swift Ruby JavaScript Objective C
Objective C plus plus C++ and C and then
you know like CSS and all that right so
that's kind of interesting so it's the
the actual UI of tuple is primarily a
webview then it sounds like and then yep
you're using Swift I guess to
communicate I guess with the operating
system level api's when possible and if
it's not possible then you kind of go
down into Objective C or C or C++ just
based on whether or not the API you're
talking to is written and C or C++ yep
that's essentially how I would think
about it and sort of I guess in the end
like when you look at all the code that
you've written for the
project you know is what is most of the
project written in it's a good question
I can probably have github just tell me
when I look at the thing
alright so 40% Swift 20% C++ 20 % CSS
10% JavaScript 10% objective-c 5%
objective c plus plus 1% other so
probably like like text files readme
files documentation stuff like that mmm
interesting it's a big break down it and
that's just the that's just the client
app that by the way like there's there's
also the backend app which is the Ruby
and rails app and stuff that's right
that's just the one that I'm you know
working in most the time so the the
parts that are written in swift versus
in C++ I would guess the C++ parts it's
probably working with the Lib web RTC is
that correct yep web RTC in there and
there's another C++ library used to help
out with some like Mouse coordinate
stuff that I also use C++ for now yeah
you're right primarily most of the C++
is us creating our own utilities around
WebRTC and then you said 40 percent is
Swift so like what is what is most of
that Swift code doing rendering
rendering the UI doing Diagnostics
handling different mouse modes so in the
app we have different cursor modes which
allow people to you know point out
specific things yeah just like all the
normal things involved with getting an
app like a native mac OS app running
there is a lot like authentication you
know talking to our API doing it
handling feature flags so only showing
certain features to certain people until
we've kind of validated that they're
gonna be good handling like deep linking
is the most recent thing I've been
working on so being able to you know
start a call using a special tuple URL
which enables things like Alfred
integrations or slack call integrations
talking to our analytic service to get
an idea of you know what features people
are using and what you know what we
should be focusing on I think that's
that's most of the stuff I can think of
that Swift layers doing I mean there's
also the Swift layer manages like the
state of what the UI should look like
and then it just sends that state across
the JavaScript and the JavaScript
renders it
appropriately so there's a good amount
of code dealing with that and there are
like a lot of windows that aren't WebKit
used that are native windows like the
Preferences window for like changing
various things throughout the
application so when we can we you know
we want to use the native API s and when
we think it really makes a difference or
it matters so for example when you're
guesting and you you're looking at the
screen of someone else's computer we use
the native mac OS toolbar that lets you
change all the different cursor modes
and the screen resolution and we use all
native controls for that yeah so it
seems like swift is really it almost
feels like it's sort of the part of the
application with the exception of the
c++ for the WebRTC interaction and then
you've got some of the web views for
some of your UI components but those are
kind of like the maybe the three main
parts yep yeah that's that's a good
break down cool I guess my next question
would be when you were working on the
project was there anything you found
much easier than you thought it would be
mm-hmm yeah I think that the call stats
ended up being a lot quicker so for some
context in the tuple application you
know one of the unique opportunities we
have because our user base is primarily
developers they're somewhat technical
and so we actually exposed the stats of
the call well to pool session is going
so you can see things like the frame
rate that's being sent the frame rate
that's being output how long it's taken
to encode or frame or decode a frame
what the available bandwidth is and all
these stats that are very useful if you
kind of know this space and are somewhat
technical we I created like a little
dashboard interface to to show that
stuff and it ended up being a lot
quicker than I anticipated primarily
because WebRTC is so great like they
provide these raw stat reports that that
they're getting from the rtcp which we
talked about at the very beginning of
the call and yeah that ended up being a
lot quicker then I I mean that honestly
I didn't even talk to Ben and roll about
doing that just one weekend I was like
it'd be really nice if I had some
dashboards to be able to look at what's
going on in a call so when I'm debugging
things I can figure out you know when I
changed this
does this get faster or slower and so
that would be one thing that took a lot
quicker and that another thing I would
say is the webcam I was very scared
about introducing the webcam after we
spent whatever it was ten months working
on only screens but it ended up being
very quick and painless and that's
definitely a testament to you know the
Google engineers and WebRTC as a whole
and I think it definitely helped that I
knew web work to see a lot more
intimately when I did that
implementation and I guess I should have
realized that at the time that like oh
man I actually know a lot about this now
and it probably won't be too bad but I
was very scared at the prospect of
having to add that into the application
yeah was the the main thing you were
worried about was it like the capturing
from the webcam like he kind of weren't
sure what that was gonna be like or what
were you thinking I guess I was worried
about the UX of it so how it would
affect the current call experience I was
worried about the bandwidth concerns so
webcam eating up a lot of bandwidth
making the screen less reliable or even
eating up so much bandwidth that you
know data channel messages get delayed
and and then that experience like the
remote control experience gets
downgraded because of it I was worried I
was worried about just even the very
basic things like making adding the
additional stream and getting it all set
up correctly at that time I was using
WebRTC in a little bit more of a naive
way when it came to like establishing
the connection there's what's called a
transceiver API which you can get a
little bit deep into most tutorials
don't really talk about it but basically
a transceiver is an RTP sender and an
RTP receiver and you can set those
transceivers up to be like
bi-directional or one-way so you can
either you know just receive audio or
can send and receive audio and I had to
do a pretty major refactor of how our
web RTC code worked in order to use
those newer api's that had been like
when we originally had set it up like
there wasn't really any push to be using
those API is like it was fine to use the
old stream based API so yeah basically
there was a big refactor that was going
to touch major critical pieces of the
code base that was really worth a big
part of the concern was but it ended up
working out great and you know web
receipts doing what would it
says it's gonna do so very grateful nice
yeah I mean it's sort of like like
you've you've kind of been talking about
how there's so many things built into
website RTC that if the way they do it
meets your use case then it's kind of
like you know boom you just kind of use
it and you're good and it's only when
you're a little bit outside of what they
do in the browser or whatnot that you
have to kind of dive in and start doing
something custom yeah definitely and and
one day and you know I very much hope to
actually not use the video pipeline and
WebRTC and build a completely custom to
pool pipeline I honestly like don't know
I have some ideas on how I would go
about doing it but I'm not confident
enough in my abilities to like think
that I could do better than WebRTC is
doing right now for us I do think that
there are a lot of trade-offs that Weber
TC is making which in our specific use
case we might not really want so for
example like they have a pretty big
jitter buffer which will ensure that if
packets are missing or get lost like
it'll it'll just wait until it gets them
but in two bowl like what we prefer to
do is just drop the frame completely at
a set rate and so it's like if I'm not
getting all the packets I need by you
know whatever my target FPS is then like
just don't even wait in the jitter
buffer just like forget about it and
there are there are like knobs and
whistles you can tune in WebRTC to kind
of make those decisions but having
complete control over it all seems
appealing to me so one day maybe we'll
we'll kind of get more in that direction
which would be awesome I think there's a
lot of low-hanging fruit in the
performance of to pool still it's just
like this last year has been so much of
just leveling up all the skills we need
it as a team in order to execute like
the v1 and now you know next year is
going to be a lot of improving the
performance and adding in more and more
unique features that just make the
pairing experience even better yeah it
sounds like you've built up this really
solid base of knowledge you know both in
native development and in WebRTC and all
that and so it sounds like you guys are
in a really good position to kind of go
into what's next yeah thanks definitely
feels that way I feel like a week worth
of work right now is was like multiple
weeks of work even just six months ago
Thanks it's a the the growth is
compounding for sure one of the things
that
I believe you've mentioned before is
that you have to use some level of
low-level graphics rendering or learned
a little bit about metal on Mac OS why
was this necessary is this for like the
screen capture or what was that for
no so the metal part is actually on the
the render phase so the core reason why
I wanted to learn about how that whole
like section of of the the process works
is just because think it's important to
not like have everything be a black box
and getting a basic understanding into
how like graphics and OpenGL works the
difference between a vertex shader and a
fragment shader how to send you know
those shaders and that your compiled
program to the GPU like that's all stuff
that I didn't I wanted to know enough
about that it wasn't just this like
scary black box to me if that makes
sense and so WebRTC provided a metal
renderer already and it's it's good it
works there's I know for a fact like
when reading through the code there's
things I can do to optimize it a bit
there's some pixel conversions that
don't need to be happening like they're
happening twice type of thing but for
the most part there was only like one
bug with it that we have to fix for
Catalina so I haven't had to do too much
work on that but the most important
thing for me was being able to read that
code and understand what was going on
and then also I probably have somewhat
of a selfish reason to want to learn it
because one day I want to build a game
engine and that's a big part of building
a game engine is figuring out how to do
the rendering piece so nice yeah I mean
I think like just in general not even on
specifically with WebRTC like it's
always good I think to go like maybe one
level deeper than kind of where you're
at like at one level of abstraction you
know lower and that way if things are
not working the way that you expect at
the higher level you kind of have a
little bit of insight into to what to do
next yeah definitely and I think
learning about the whole rendering
process and how metal works enabled me
to be able to do that piece of code
where I white out or black out the
screen where the webcam is like I
probably could have figured that out
without that knowledge but understanding
at least a little bit more about how
that whole subsystem works definitely
made that be like a one-hour thing
instead of a one-week type of thing
for sure if you were starting over
knowing what you know now are they are
there any things that you would have
done differently
I think it would be less inclined to
want to use action cable we've been
using action cable as our signaling
service and there's been a lot of like
weird wonky things with it and it's very
hard to debug and I don't know I think I
would have preferred to just use like
socket IO or some some other service
that's maybe a little bit more mature in
the wild or it's been used in the wild
longer but that seems like relatively
small thing in the grand scheme of
things I mean in an ideal world I wish I
could start over and have all the
knowledge I have right now about the
space and the programming languages the
one thing I would say is I'm very
grateful like Swift and makes it very
easy to refactor like safely which is
great so like as I've learned more about
Swift development and Mac OS development
I've been able to kind of rejigger some
of the application to be architected a
little bit more effectively without you
know too much pain like if I was using
something like Ruby for that it would
have been a lot more painful but that's
I don't know it started to say yeah yeah
don't don't have a good answer right I
mean hindsight is yeah hindsight's 20/20
so and also for the listeners action
cable being the WebSocket I guess
implementation for Ruby on Rails right
yep thanks for clarifying that and
socket IO being the equivalent for
nodejs yep yeah I don't know I'm pretty
happy with the decisions we made there's
nothing like super bad that stands out
like man if we had done this one thing
differently our life would be a lot
easier right now I guess the the way
that we set up the calls so early on you
know we kind of had this idea that it
would always be peer to peer one-to-one
like your pair programming with someone
well we didn't fully realize is that a
lot of people do what's called mob pair
programming where they have multiple
people in a session but both Ben and I
who like have more of a background in
pairing like we never did that we've
always only paired like one to one right
and so a lot of the internals of tuple
where it was like very much set up in a
way where it was only meant for two
people and I don't fully regret that
decision because I would say that the
code base was less complex by by doing
it that way like there were
less that we had to think about and it
allowed us to get the app going a lot
faster and we were able to get to market
we were able to course-correct and make
these small changes that people wanted
in order for us to become profitable and
be able to do this as like a full-time
thing but if we had had funding and
unlimited time I probably would have bit
the bullet and you know added that
complexity into the app right from the
start and the complexity part being just
the ability to start a call with like n
number of people but yeah now we're kind
of past that like we the code base is
set up in a way where that's no longer
that much of an issue so I don't feel
too too bad about it anymore
but I remember at the time dreading
dreading that having to do that yeah I
mean in some ways though it's probably
it may have been good to start with just
one on one because then it really helped
you guys focus right just on the one use
case make sure that use case is really
solid and not kind of get distracted
with you know things that not as many
people use yeah a hundred percent also
this is such a great example of you know
I don't know product development but so
we felt like we were getting so many
requests for doing n number calls and
back in the early days when we didn't
support that and then since supporting
it like the percentage of people that
actually do it is probably less than ten
percent it's tiny yeah and so like I bet
if we just didn't have that feature it
would still just be fine
right yeah but we would probably get
some complaints about it and really it
like the the challenge would be to keep
a good psychological state and know that
people are requesting something you know
they don't actually want or use that
often but yeah it's it's funny how that
works like people a lot of people be
very loud about a certain thing but then
not a lot of your users actually end up
getting value from that or wanting to or
needing that feature so right it's yeah
that's tricky cuz you don't know until
you actually give it to them right
totally
so finally is there anything you wish
you had while developing the application
that could be a feature in WebRTC that
could be an open source library is there
anything that would have made things a
lot easier for you yeah I mean this is
not code related but I wish I had had
multiple powerful machines soon
hmm this sounds ridiculous but like I
had my one main laptop for programming
on and for a while I was just using
these old laptops as like my Pierre
number two pure number three was
developing the app and for a while I
only just had like my one monitor and
then they used laptop screens and like I
don't know why I guess I was so worried
about running out of runway because we
weren't making money for a while that I
didn't just invest in having you know
multiple monitors and like multiple new
brand new machines that are powerful and
it's just like my dev life now is
significantly improved now that I have
that so that's definitely a big regret
something I wish I had had as far as
code goes you know I really wish that if
I didn't need to learn C++ to have made
tuple I would think I would be a happier
person that maybe sounds somewhat
cynical but I imagine C++ is great if
you're really good at it and even doing
it for a really long time but the one
thing I know about myself is like I'm I
don't know I it's very easy for you to
shoot yourself in the foot in C++ and I
have made like all of the classic
mistakes in C++ and it definitely makes
me wish that there was like a rust
implementation of WebRTC or you know
some other language there is actually a
go implementation of web RTC called peon
or PI on not sure how to pronounce it
which is very exciting to me definitely
worth checking out if you're looking for
you know trying to get your feet wet and
more like a side project D type of thing
with WebRTC and you know go or you like
go
I would I would check that out because
it seems very cool to me but it
obviously it had it's not as robust as
the C++ implementation that's been
around for you know 10 years or whatever
yeah it'll be interesting to see if
there's because I think like when people
hear WebRTC they're usually thinking of
sort of the browser use cases you know
someone doing video chat or sure audio
chat that sort of thing and so and yeah
it'll be interesting to see if more
people are using it in kind of the
native space and if that sort of
encourages the use of a binding in rust
or like you said building out more and
go that sort of thing yeah I mean even a
full implementation and rest not just a
binding would be would be cool you know
I think that if the if the Google
engineers and I mean I know there's a
lot of Mozilla engineers that
on WebRTC as well I bet if rust was you
know what it is now but back then when
they started they probably would have
chosen rust but you know is what it is
maybe not I mean they interface with
chromium so maybe they wouldn't have
made that decision but that's true
trying to think of other things that I
wish I had had I wish I had been more
open to talking to experts early on so I
think there was a little bit of pride
involved in like me not wanting to just
use these resources like oh I need to
figure it out myself
and every single time that we did a call
with an expert on some specific area
that I was interested in the value that
we got from that in the amount I learned
was you know 10 or 20 X how much we
spent on it and I think the next company
that I do if there is ever another one
outside of to pool I'm gonna allocate a
budget towards talking to experts but
it's gonna be a budget that I have to
spend right so it's like there's this
much money in the bank account each
month like you it needs to be spent on
somebody giving me some information and
the crazy thing is a lot of people just
ended up helping us for free even though
we offered to pay them and that's
definitely something I've been very
grateful for I can't believe how many
people in the community of like just
offered their help or their expertise so
so I guess a lot of people just want to
see this exist in the world and that's
been fantastic but yeah a dedicated
budget to experts would be another one
that's awesome if you're stuck on
something you know sometimes just
talking to an expert is like you know
makes such a huge difference it could
cut out like a week of time you would
have spent struggling with something so
yeah yeah and when it when you're
pre-revenue like a week feels so long
it's so interesting cool time is trippy
well I think kind of ready to wrap up
but is there anything else that you
think I should have asked and I think
you did an awesome job if if people want
to check out to pool they can get a
two-pole tap it's our website and yeah
my twitter is my name Spencer C Dixon so
definitely reach out if people have
questions or anything like that
fantastic so Spencer thank you so much
for coming on the show no problem
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening